A Guide to the Thomas R. McCullough Collection, 1772-1875
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Thomas R. McCullough Collection, 1772-1875
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-110
0.25 linear feet
The Thomas R. McCullough Collection consists of 0.25 linear feet and spans the years 1772-1875, and contains land records, surveys, correspondence, and unidentified photographs.
McCullough, Thomas R. (1922-2020)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Penelope Carboni, stepdaughter of Thomas R. McCullough, September 2021.
Historical and Biographical Information
On July 1, 1772, James Deneal (1728-1806) took out a land grant for 552 acres between Piney Branch and Popes Head Creek in what is today Fairfax Station, Virginia. The property later passed to his son, George DeNeale (1762-1818). In 1856, his daughter Ann Lucretia Stuart (?-1871) sold the land to John Bathurst Daingerfield (1817-1886). Daingerfield later purchased “Rose Hill” in Franconia and sold the property to his friend Thomas D. Addison (1845-1925) in 1875.
Addison named one of his children after Daingerfield, John Daingerfield Addison (1888-1966). Thomas D. Addison made his home on the property which was called “Bathurst” off present-day Fairfax Station Road. Until recently, a concrete gate post at the end of the long driveway up to the farmhouse had “Bathurst” engraved in it. Longtime residents of Fairfax Station recall there being Civil War graffiti on the dining room wall of the house.
The property was inherited by John Daingerfield Addison and his sister, Bland Addison Wilkinson (1889-1986), upon their mother’s passing in December 1938. Bland and her husband Theodore Wilkinson had a child named Mary Jacqueline Wilkinson (1917-1984) who grew up in “Bathurst”. She married Thomas Rougier McCullough (1922-2020) at Fort Myer in Arlington, Virginia on October 24, 1949.
After John Daingerfield Addison’s passing in 1966, Bland and Mary inherited the remaining 289 acres and had it partitioned. Bland sold 50 acres to Mary in December 1969. After the passing of his wife in 1984, and his mother-in-law in 1986, Thomas R. McCullough became the owner of both Mary’s and Bland’s properties. In 1992, several acres of the property were taken by the Commonwealth for construction of the Fairfax County Parkway, which split up the farm. McCullough sold the remaining 33 acres to Knollwood Baptist Church in 1997. Presently, Daingerfield Way and Smoke Rise Lane run through what was once the family farm. The documents in this collection were found among McCullough’s belongings after he passed away at age 98 in Warminster, Pennsylvania on December 24, 2020.
Scope and Content
The Thomas R. McCullough Collection consists of 0.25 linear feet and spans the years 1772-1875, and contains land records, surveys, correspondence, and unidentified photographs. This collection of records pertains to his first wife, Mary Jacqueline McCullough’s family farm in Fairfax Station, Virginia, of which he later inherited. The home on the property was at one time known as “Bathurst” named for original owner John Bathurst Daingerfield.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Addison, Thomas D. (1845-1925); Daingerfield, John Bathurst (1817-1886); Deneal, James (1728-1806); Deneale, Edward (1762-1800); Deneale, James (1770-1821); DeNeale, George (1762-1818); Fairfax Station (Va.) - History; McCullough, Thomas R. (1922-2020); Stuart, Ann Lucretia Stuart (?-1871); Taylor, Lawrence B. (1818-1873)
Container List
- Northern Neck Land Grant, James Deneal, 1772 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Deed, James Deneale to Edward Deneale, 1795 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Deed, James Deneale to James and George Deneale, 1795 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Deed of Gift, James Deneale to Edward Deneale [fragments], 1795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Survey, James Deneale, George Deneale, and Edward Deneale, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Deed, James Deneale to George Deneale, 1798 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bill of Sale, James Deneale to George Deneale, 1799 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Deed, James Deneale and Precilla Deneale to George Deneale, 1801 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter, Lawrence B. Taylor to John B. Daingerfield, 1856 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Deed, Ann L. Stuart to John B. Daingerfield, 1856 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Survey, Stuart and Daingerfield, 1858 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter, John B. Daingerfield to Thomas D. Addison, 1874 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Deed, John B. Daingerfield and Rebecca Daingerfield to Thomas D. Addison, 1875 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photo, unidentified man (Theodore Wilkinson?), Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photo, unidentified man (Theodore Wilkinson?), Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photo, unidentified woman (Bland Addison?), Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)